[SPEAKER_01]: That's one thing that people would really struggle to understand when we say, like, the... in order to enter the first jhāna, you factually have to give up even the liability to the five hindrances, not just, like, specific manifestations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then it would sound like, also, you're saying you have to basically become an arahant in order to enter the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the liability to the hindrances is factually gone at that time, whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean that they will not come back.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if you incline the mind, if you give in to the things that, at that time, don't feel like they're a problem, the hindrances will return.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I thought we could discuss mindfulness from the perspective of losing mindfulness, let's say, because we already talked in the past about the four satipaṭṭhānas, and to some extent we discussed the hindrances and things like that, but it was more on a broader level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think, first of all, we could start by defining what is mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when many people hear that word, they might confuse it with a moment-to-moment focused awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that very reason, they wouldn't necessarily realize how they lose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they would think that, you know, if I just... if I can just focus more, focus harder, not have any external circumstances,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can we define mindfulness in a more accurate way?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, not necessarily focusing on the angle of mindfulness, you could also call it samādhi or composure, because it goes hand in hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solidified mindfulness is basically the same as composure being established.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, experientially, how does it feel to have mindfulness established, let's say?
[SPEAKER_03]: Still, calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a result of the mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can be still or calm, actually, due to lack of mindfulness as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Having a perspective upon the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be one way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But is that perspective something that you are kind of actively maintaining?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the right mindfulness is based on understanding what is already there, given.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, the mindfulness is the recollection or the remembering of
[SPEAKER_02]: Those aspects of your experience that have to be there already.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, those things you don't need to maintain.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, then the question is, or I think this is what you're asking, like, so one can recollect those things which are like satipaṭṭhāna, or death, or asupa, or any context that you set up,
[SPEAKER_02]: That is the direction of the right mindfulness, but then that context or the perspective can be lost.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, we're working towards finding out what are the factors that one falls away from that context, but those things that you were established in, in and of themselves, they don't go anywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but at the same time, the mindfulness itself, the perspective over those things, is it something you do or is it something that... or is it not something you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you just say that it's already there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you just say it like that, then it sounds like you don't have to do anything and we're already enlightened or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's clearly not the meaning here.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, so you do need to understand
[SPEAKER_02]: Those aspects or principles to begin with, because otherwise you can't correctly recollect them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that won't be the right perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you do, in a sense, need to set it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you do that properly, then, in a sense, your mindfulness will be there on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not going to be like that from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So there is an aspect of understanding,
[SPEAKER_02]: And there is an aspect of establishing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you have to just let it endure on its own.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the question is, how are you going to find out once it's been lost?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point I'm trying to highlight is that, when mindfulness is established,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's important to recognize it's not something you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to work to clarify it and understand it, as you said.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once it's there, it's kind of there on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's containing you, in a way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not something that you are doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is actually precisely one of the reasons why, if you're not careful, you will lose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it feels like you don't need to maintain it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Precisely because of that, factual fact, in a sense, you don't need to maintain it anymore, but you overlook that there are things that you could do that will slowly degrade what you've built up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said it's a perspective, but
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a perspective of something specific?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it like a specific thought that endures in your mind?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or is it something else?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the perspective is of the totality, quote-unquote, of this experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that is part of the understanding, right?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as we discussed with the satipaṭṭhāna, that there are four, let's say, phenomenological totalities.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they all... they're slightly different vantage points, but they disclose your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is... that would be the right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's not like that, and you're going to focus on something specific, it will always be, as we said many times, in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you try to focus on that very hard, and then the whole question of distraction comes in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, there's going to be a conflict between looking at that glass and a particular thought arising, and I feel I need to suppress it because I want to focus on the thing there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then all of that comes along, which actually has nothing really to do with what we're talking about now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, assuming that that wrong direction is out of the way, then the mindfulness is about understanding this situation as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but is there a specific... is it that the mindfulness has a specific theme?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it tied to it, or is it something that's not linked to a specific theme?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you choose to develop mindfulness of feelings, is it that just feelings is what comes up for your perspective only?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you want to be mindful of something else, you have to change your object?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that how it works, or...?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have discerned feeling on that most general level, then your mindfulness can be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, there will be mindfulness of feeling, and then, within that, all sorts of other things can take place, but that will not be in conflict with being mindful of that general feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, so what I'm pointing at is, mindfulness is a kind of a... it's a quality in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not defined by... it's just a broadening of perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness, you could say, is the broadening of perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it doesn't matter whether that broadening of perspective is kind of instantiated through perspective of the body, perspective of feelings, perspective of mind, perspective of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have developed that mindfulness properly, on the right level,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of these four things you could take up for reflection with the same mindfulness that you've built up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, it's just like a space, let's say, a space that opens up and then that space can be filled in with any, any, basically anything you, that takes your fantasy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another... the reason why I'm bringing that up is because that dispels the whole notion of it being about locking your mind into one specific thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can think of it as, on a very wrong, extremely wrong level, of thinking of it as a specific object of concentrated focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if you start thinking about it as a context or a theme or a reflection,
[SPEAKER_00]: You might also still have some lingering notion that it's about, like, maintain... like, keeping those... keeping your mind within that specific topic.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not necessarily the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the mindfulness is just the ability... it's just the perspective, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ability to see your experience for what it is at any given time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a sense of clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... so...
[SPEAKER_05]: Having said that, then, how is it that you will lose it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's not about keeping it tied to the same theme, even, it's not that I'll need to be thinking about feelings the whole evening in order to develop mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, it's a direction, so you could cultivate it in multiple different ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how is it that you will lose it, given that it's not tied to a specific thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not tied to a specific thing, but clearly, it does get lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that it's just like, once you establish mindfulness properly, that's it, you're done and become an Arhat.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any ideas, anyone?
[SPEAKER_03]: By accepting the light and
[SPEAKER_03]: Entertaining that relief that other sensuality or, let's say, doubt, for example, presents you with.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, generally, it would begin with, like, subtler things or, like, minor things, but then each time you kind of prioritize that relief, you are basically
[SPEAKER_01]: And why is it... why does it present itself as relief?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're kind of already clear about the fact that that's not where relief comes from, why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you still give in?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mindfulness... it's clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know that this is... to a certain extent, you might already be experiencing the right type of relief, of giving up, of perspective, of dispassion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it still... why would you still accept it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because of the habit, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, yeah, that's on a broader scale, but at that moment, like, what is it that makes you... Oh, pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Discomfort.
[SPEAKER_05]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're seeing that discomfort as not yours, as something that arose on its own because your mindfulness is established, then why do you... why would you still do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think you would.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, but what I'm saying, you could have the clarity that, oh, this is arisen on its own, this is not mine, this is impermanent, and all this stuff, and yet you would give it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you wouldn't see the danger?
[SPEAKER_05]: Sure, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: Like if you... the thing is, like we said before, the mindfulness is not even something that you actively do.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, in a way, the clarity that it is dangerous, that it is impermanent, that it is suffering, that it is not yours, that clarity would be enduring there even, like, regardless of what you do.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if you don't actively think about, oh, this is dangerous, you know that it's dangerous because the mindfulness is established on that peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, given that that's... despite the fact that's there, you would give in.
[SPEAKER_05]: What?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's as close as you can get.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just carelessness.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not that you don't know that it's not the right direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know that it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the carelessness is, in a way,
[SPEAKER_05]: By putting the wrong emphasis on like... because, see, you could take it either way.
[SPEAKER_05]: You take it as... when you have that clarity and it feels like, you know, everything is... you see things as they are, as Buddha would say, it can feel as if, okay, so it doesn't matter what I do then, because this clarity is going to be there anyway.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you could take that in two directions.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter what I do.
[SPEAKER_05]: Therefore, I would break my restraint and give in to the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_05]: And factually, the clarity will not fade away immediately.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it kind of precedes the domain of action.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or you could take it the other way and say, well, it doesn't matter what I do, so let me not do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let me not give in.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the thing is, it's like, the clarity, the domain of the mind in general, it's not something... it's always indirect.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not something that you can kind of measure, like, this is how much mindfulness I have.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what you would do is, like, you would give in,
[SPEAKER_05]: And, eh... you kind of check, okay, it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: I haven't lost it.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's still there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you feel like, okay, well, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: Let me just fully go wild.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, eh... and later on, you would look back and you realize, oh, wait, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_05]: Abruptly, you just realize, oh, wait, it's gone.
[SPEAKER_05]: You didn't even see, eh... there was no warning sign.
[SPEAKER_05]: There was nothing.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the same way that there was no warning sign when you were developing it properly, you suddenly realized, oh, wait,
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been, I've been, like, as that simile says, like, wearing down the axe handle.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've been wearing it down, and suddenly you realize, oh, now I cannot even forget that things are impermanent, that the body comes first, all these things.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, okay, now mindfulness is established.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, so, yeah, it works both ways.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why it's, it's important to, to, to be clear that it's that
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a dimension that doesn't depend on you, because then, first, that would allow you to develop it properly, and secondly, it would also allow you to protect it, because if you're still putting the emphasis on, like,
[SPEAKER_05]: Your kind of aspect of the equation, you forget that actually there's... like, you may not feel any problem with doing these things that go against the direction that you've developed, but there is that kind of a delayed effect that these things will lead to, and it always snowballs.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the more you give in, the kind of easier it gets to continue in that direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: So...
[SPEAKER_05]: And what is it that you would give in to, specifically?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, let's say, somebody... you might not even break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be assumed that, you know, if you even got to the point where your mindfulness was established, you were already established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is it that, despite not breaking the precepts, you would still lose your mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, it has to start with mental action, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you're not gonna act out by body unless you've been welcoming thoughts related to acting out by body.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's more subtle than breaking the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you can almost, like, not to say that it's, like, accidental, but... Well, I guess, if you are mindful, you can't overlook it.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you are partly mindful, you won't overlook it, but kind of like you say, you can just kind of see it as, oh, well, you know,
[SPEAKER_04]: This is insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's another point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it accidental?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because I think there's often this perception that, um, you know, people are... do kind of get a sense of, oh, yeah, I've developed this clarity because I've been doing this 10-day retreat, and then they would still have the sense that when they go back, it's kind of like, because of the external world and because of the situations that they have to face,
[SPEAKER_01]: Those external things are making them lose their mindfulness accidentally.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, eh... if it's not accidental, as you said, it's related to mental action, but eh... the important thing to see is that, like, that mental action isn't just... like, it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a simple failure to protect the same thing that you were already doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not even like some secret information that you didn't have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, unfortunately, they told you how to build up the mindfulness, but nobody taught you how to maintain it, as if it's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's literally the same context that you've been maintaining.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's still there.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you, like we said before, carelessly choose to just emphasize the other stuff.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, but what are the things that would take you in that opposite direction, let's say?
[SPEAKER_03]: Detection, company, work.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Those are kind of the external things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as we said, mentally, even before you give in by body and speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: He nurses.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, as you read in the suttas, it's like, they say, weakeners of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or, like, they constrict the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that constriction is
[SPEAKER_05]: 100% exactly the opposite direction of the broader perspective that mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you don't even have... that's exactly why, even without breaking the precepts, you would still be able to
[SPEAKER_05]: Emphasize the wrong direction and pretty much willingly wear away your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, yeah, restlessness, doubt, and let's say you develop some clarity about
[SPEAKER_05]: Some aspect of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you saw that, oh, what the dhamma, the practice, is to not act out of painful feelings.
[SPEAKER_05]: But before, that was just theory, that was just information.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, you're seeing it on that experiential level.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have that clarity developed.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then, doubts come up, questions come up, about things that you know are secondary, things that you know are... that you know that what matters is not acting out of unpleasant feelings, and you know that any type of actually relevant wisdom would come out of that, wouldn't come out of you clarifying abstract ideas.
[SPEAKER_05]: But still,
[SPEAKER_05]: The pressure is just too much for you to stick to what you already know is right.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's basically that.
[SPEAKER_05]: A simple choice to not protect the same thing that was already there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, like you were saying before, you kind of know.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, if somebody were to just suddenly, I don't know, break into your room and ask you a question at that moment, which is a wholesome thing to do?
[SPEAKER_05]: To go through with that doubt or to see that as a painful feeling that's pressuring you and not act out of it?
[SPEAKER_05]: You would give the right answer.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why it's basically gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_04]: You might not be asking yourself that, though, necessarily.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: You know, but then you choose to pretty much put aside the clarity that you yourself have.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's a self-induced
[SPEAKER_05]: Problem, let's say.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the same way that the development of mindfulness cannot be... cannot happen accidentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that... that, you know, you just get put in the right environment and suddenly it develops on its own.
[SPEAKER_05]: There is no way for that to... to build up unless you have been doing the right things.
[SPEAKER_05]: You may not recognize it in hindsight that you were doing the right things because
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe you haven't had the right information sufficiently, or you haven't reflected on it enough, so you wouldn't be able to do it again.
[SPEAKER_05]: But factually, it's something that you would have had to work for, let's say.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because the direction of pressure, the direction of hindrances, is... like nobody will accidentally stop
[SPEAKER_05]: Giving into that, because every reward that that anybody can conceivably know of, lies in that direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Lies in the direction of acting out.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, without faith, without some degree of, let's say, higher motivation, there is no way that you can just endure that pain and maintain the clarity of feelings, the body, all the things this is talked about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you know if you're acting out of hindrances?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, obviously, this is not something that would be externally defined by... in the way the precepts are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, just don't do this, and you won't be acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's only to a certain extent, which is the extent of the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do those things, you're acting out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_05]: But beyond that, is there a way to know internally?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is going to be rude and hindrance, and what is not?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you could you could check whether that perspective is established.
[SPEAKER_04]: That we've been talking about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, but it is going to be included, because that's how mindfulness works.
[SPEAKER_04]: When it's there, everything is included.
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_05]: How would you be able to know that this action that's being presented to you right now by your own mind,
[SPEAKER_05]: That it's going to take you away from this clarity.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, that it's a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't... because it's... you don't even need to use the... classify it into, oh, it's this type of hindrance, it's that type of hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be able to just directly see, this is the opposite direction of what I've cultivated.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how would you know?
[SPEAKER_04]: What comes to mind if I was to abstain from following action, it would be unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, that's one way you could look at it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, anything that the mind feels
[SPEAKER_01]: Apprehensive, when you even tease the option of saying no to it, that already shows you that there's probably gratification and infatuation involved with that action.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, because, see, that is what makes the mind unwilling to basically have the clarity that you yourself want to develop.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's the fact that, like,
[SPEAKER_05]: When you don't have that clarity, you can be having the same thoughts, and the same reflections, and the same encouragements for the mind, and it just ignores them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't listen to them, and it insists in being concerned instead with sight, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, worries about the past, concerns about the future.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's when you basically
[SPEAKER_05]: push it in any direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: Actually, you would be able to know in advance, like, oh, this will... if I do this, the mind will become agitated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you could also say, the mind won't listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can simply put, like, when you have a dog, and, you know, you kind of have it
[SPEAKER_00]: on a closed leash, and it's listening to you, and it's kind of obedient.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you let it go a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, the more you let it go, the harder it's going to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, like, if you let it go, depending on the attitude that it has, depending on the behavior that it's showing, you can see, like, what that engagement will result in.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the dog is calm, and you let it walk, well, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see that it's already getting in that kind of excitement mode, and you actually let it go, what you will see is, it's going to be three times harder to bring it back afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you have to recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to stop being concerned with, like, the kind of external definitions of what is allowable and what is not allowable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If something... if you see that, at that moment,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not yesterday, not tomorrow, not ten years ago.
[SPEAKER_00]: At that moment, that dog is kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting into that mode of agitation towards this action that might be externally praiseworthy and externally, you know, considered, whatever, virtuous, then you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is at that, like, what is a hindrance and what is not a hindrance, is going to be determined by your own mind, not by you and your kind of classification and your preference of... That's why it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, it is a fundamental truth or fundamental principle, but at the same time, that doesn't mean it's public.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is to be experienced individually by the wise, because only in relation to your own mind can you know what is a hindrance and what is not, what is wholesome and what is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's universal, but subjective.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's... you cannot make a kind of... again, apart from the precepts, you cannot make a list of things that are always leading you astray.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that would be then the precepts, but within that...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to determine from within the situation that you're in, which includes which feeling is present, what mood is going on there, which are precisely these satipaṭṭhāna, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those, you want to keep an eye on, because
[SPEAKER_02]: From day to day, it might change.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you could come up with the perfect list that is tailored specifically to your mind and your mind's tendencies, it'll just change.
[SPEAKER_05]: It doesn't matter, because it changes from day to day.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like you can make a list of things that, in the past, would have led to hindrances, and you may well overlook that your attitude of list building, at that very moment, is really aggressive.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or doubt.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's something that the mind is, with that same agitation, engaging with.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it can only be seen presently and in that peripheral dimension of, like,
[SPEAKER_05]: What is this going to do to my mind?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it going to make it more obedient or less obedient?
[SPEAKER_05]: Just on that general level.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't even have to think in terms of, like, how does this action relate to the body or feelings or something like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is this animal going to listen to me less and be concerned with the world as a result of me letting it do this?
[SPEAKER_05]: And even if those things that it's concerned with are not as bad as the things that you let go through the precepts, let's say, it's still... the fact that it is going to become disobedient, that is bad in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter if it becomes disobedient for, like, you know, things that are... that are... that other people may regard as fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the suttas would say that, eh... like a noble disciple would be... would be, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's basically hindered from progressing further if they become overly engaged with talk, sleep and work, which none of them are against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's the fact that they kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: Again, push the mind into that mode where it's not going to listen to you and where it's not going to be pliable for developing the contexts and taking it into directions that it has to go, which is dispassion, relinquishment, cessation.
[SPEAKER_05]: That alone is a problem.
[SPEAKER_05]: That it's going to make the mind disobedient.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that needs to be... Once the precepts are established, the standard needs to be upgraded to that much more general level of, like, leading to pliability of mind, leading away from pliability of mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: And... and, eh... it's... it's... it's important as well to see that the...
[SPEAKER_05]: Attitude of denying everything, that's another trap, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, it's not that if you say no to everything, you're going to make it that much more pliable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, if I could just say no to everything, then, oh, well, everything's fixed, right?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, if only it were that easy.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because, in and of itself, that
[SPEAKER_01]: engagement of saying no to things, that very much can be written in aversion, which is another one of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, um... it's it's a it's a kind of balancing act, almost, and you have to
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even trial and error, because trial and error kind of implies that you... that you will find like a fixed answer at a certain point.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not... you don't find an answer to... to what is a hindrance and what isn't, and how to calm the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just understand the broader principle that you're able to apply in each individual circumstance.
[SPEAKER_04]: That training of the mind, or making it more pliable, as we were saying, is that only discerned through... like, does that have to be discerned through feeling?
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's not like I can just think about it abstractly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that has to be... yeah, to know what choice to make has to be felt.
[SPEAKER_05]: Basically, yeah, you have to feel it, quote-unquote, at that moment.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have to feel... because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: The mind is... like... it's not something that you would be able to overlook.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or, let's say, it's... you would certainly be able to overlook it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not something that can be actually absent from your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just that if you don't look in that direction, like... it's just a simple kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a glimpse of how is the mind kind of reacting to this, or what kind of disposition or behavior is it showing when it looks in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's that feeling that's felt at that moment, if it's, as the suttas would say, the joy and pleasure on account of
[SPEAKER_01]: Mundane things, that's what you shouldn't cultivate.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said that pleasure should be feared, should be shunned, should be avoided.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not the external sense objects, but the feeling that you see on the level of the mind, when it's inclining towards those things.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what has to be avoided.
[SPEAKER_05]: And on the other hand, if there's no feeling there, that there's no feeling of pleasure on that mental level,
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is, let's say, I don't know, the classic example, it wants to go for a walk.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's no like kind of obsessive sense of pleasure associated with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't really care that much if you don't do it either.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, you have to see, oh wait, well, I don't have to say no to this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if you do, then you're... if you do say no to it, it means you're emphasizing something other than the actual discernment of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just using your preconceived notions of
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I shouldn't do this, because such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and on the other hand as well, with aversion, like if you, if you realize, let's say, avoid, avoiding certain types of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when is that actually aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: And when is it just
[SPEAKER_01]: Acting according to intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's that's how you would know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is the mind internally upset and agitated about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, is it going to kind of rebel and complain?
[SPEAKER_01]: If I don't let it avoid this, well, then you may want to think twice about
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of like thinking you can train a dog.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, when it does something wrong, you hate it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, it's not doing anything wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you think, well, might as well hit it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will make it more obedient.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't put your hands just confusing the door.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it will fear you, but it won't go, well, not for the right reasons.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but now...
[SPEAKER_03]: It won't be obedient.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just won't do...
[SPEAKER_03]: It won't go anywhere, so to say, even where you would want it to go.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but if you only hit it when it is actually doing something wrong, then the message, what is wrong, would be clearer to the dog.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then it has been clouded by just a random slap here and there.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dog would just be confused, like, what's wrong with this now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so the thing is, that's why it's then important to to put aside
[SPEAKER_00]: Your notions of what's right and wrong, and base everything upon the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, discernment of the present mental state, the present mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it effective with greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it effective with aversion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it effective with delusion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as we've discussed before, that's how you would also overcome sīla-bhāta-paramāṁsa.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you would cease to emphasize any sort of preconceived notions of what... of sense of duty or sense of, like, being... being... needing to... to adhere to some kind of external standard of behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: And instead, everything would be automatically oriented by that vision of
[SPEAKER_01]: How is the mind inclining in relation to this action at this moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in an abstract sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was kind of thinking about, throughout this discussion, when Ajahn Yanamoli would say, like, it doesn't matter, kind of, if you can handle it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's if the mind can handle it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it kind of ties into like, oh, yeah, it's fine if I do this.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, that's not really what you should be focusing on.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what is the consequence going to be for the mind?
[SPEAKER_04]: When you do this, which is not necessarily going to be like it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not going to be as...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, within your control.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, like we said just now, the greater issue comes from the fact that the mind, if it's factually developed to some degree of perspective, you may not even feel the pain right away.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, factually, the mind becomes immovable.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then, you will realize only afterwards.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, when the... oh, wait, I'm sitting in the spit of burning coals again.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you... you...
[SPEAKER_05]: But, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can see already, even before you go through with it, you factually can see, that is where the mind will end up.
[SPEAKER_05]: It may not be immediate, because if it were immediate, well, you probably wouldn't go through with it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's precisely because it's kind of like far away, and you think like, oh, no, no, I'll kind of...
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll get back on track.
[SPEAKER_05]: Way before I end up in that direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's why you let it go.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you don't realize, like, it's like a snowball.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, just one little bit is enough to just keep rolling.
[SPEAKER_05]: You could stop yourself, factually, but why?
[SPEAKER_05]: Who, in their right mind, would start exciting a dog that's twice heavier than them, to want to go in the opposite direction where they want them to be in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they can't stop it, why would they risk being dragged to where they don't want to go?
[SPEAKER_03]: And what you said about the sīlabate paramāsa and seeing, well, seeing, giving up your idea of this external thing is how I train my mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: I would say it's more, well, more so than giving up what you think is this external thing that you are doing,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more about questioning what you think external means.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, like, oh, obviously I'm not doing those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Failing to see, well, there must be something you are doing in that way.
[SPEAKER_05]: Otherwise, you would have seen... Yeah, because external, of course, you know, that's what we always end up coming back to, like this common notion of rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's like, oh, the obviously external thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, to some extent, you realize that
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, if you're half-wise, you realize, yeah, that's not where the training lies.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, like, what is actually external?
[SPEAKER_05]: External could very well be still on the level of
[SPEAKER_05]: Internal, quote-unquote, practices of, like, the ways that you think you need to be reflecting or contemplating, or whatever, or the ways that you think you should be watching your intentions, or directing the mind like this, or directing the mind like that, all of that would be made external if you don't see the actual inclination of the mind at that moment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, like you might have a sense of duty, for example,
[SPEAKER_02]: Built up in the course of your life, and now you are in a situation when nothing properly external is insisting that you should perform the duty, but you still do it because you regard it as duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but even on a more accurate level, even if externally you're not... it's nothing that anybody else can see.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fully mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would... it would still be an external sīla-bhātta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be an external sense of duty, of... could be anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could be, I don't know, reflecting on death, or every day I have to be, you know, reflecting on the drawbacks and shattering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And those things are... you see, you're not even seeing, like, how is the mind planning?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it actually working?
[SPEAKER_05]: Where is it taking me?
[SPEAKER_05]: You just...
[SPEAKER_00]: Take on this kind of repetitive performance of a certain thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you get sick for half a week, or for a week, and you can't do your particular exercises, and then you feel that you are not fulfilling your duty as a monk.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then that becomes unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, the whole thing just goes downhill, because from the start it was very wrong.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to see on the acute, internal, presently arisen level, eh... as... you have to use that as a standard for what needs to be done and what doesn't need to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you would realize it works both ways.
[SPEAKER_05]: It works both in the sense that sometimes you might be overdoing it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, sometimes you might be... the mind is already
[SPEAKER_00]: In the direction of, you know, clarity and context, but you keep pushing it and prodding it with these reflections that already serve their purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which would be like, well, that would then become aimless or restlessness, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just don't know when it's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, it could work the other way around as well, that, you know, you you think, like, often with the kind of, um,
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that meditation is like this session that you do during the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it will work both ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, during the session, you think that you have to be focusing every moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't realize, like, where, when the mind is factually already clear about the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to keep repeating it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, you would think that when the session ends, that you can just do whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that actually, no, you can't press pause on the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I've done my duty, I've done my hour in the morning, and I've done my puja in the evening, so what happens during the rest of the day?
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you do two hours in the morning, then for the rest of the day you're fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: At any given time, you will have to be clear about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this might... this very reflection might become mechanical at some point.
[SPEAKER_05]: The reflection of where the intention is and how the mind is inclined towards things.
[SPEAKER_05]: That will become your external practice at some point.
[SPEAKER_05]: But you always have a chance.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you have been keeping the virtue, if you have been keeping the senses straight, and you know that you have to be self-honest,
[SPEAKER_05]: At some point, it will land on you that, oh, wait, I'm doing this now with this insane external sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then you would see, oh, okay, so that's where the mind is inclining.
[SPEAKER_05]: It wasn't like everything else that I was assuming to be the inclination of the mind was secondary.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was this very pressure that was directing me to do this.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's where it was.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's kind of the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of the ironic bit.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of those
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that you would be doing wrongly, to address the issue, you're doing precisely so as not to address the issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So as to ignore the state of the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, see, not acting out of restlessness is painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: And so that's what you're doing right then and there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, sure, you might... if somebody asks you, you would... oh, what am I doing?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah, I'm trying to not act out of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, yeah, what the mind says it's doing, and what it's actually doing, is two different things.
[SPEAKER_05]: And you need to be able to discern the latter, and not go by just what the mind kind of... what you initially... when you ask yourself, what am I doing?
[SPEAKER_05]: The first answer that comes, that's not actually the intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: When we talk about reflecting on intentions, I think we clarified that before, that
[SPEAKER_01]: Usually, you might think it's like the reasons, the reasoning behind, like the explanation behind this action.
[SPEAKER_05]: But no.
[SPEAKER_05]: You'll be more accurate to say, like, what would happen if I just stop this?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what, that's where, that's really, that kind of reflection would indirectly reveal what present inclination there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What happens if I don't do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what would determine the extent of mindfulness as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you realize, oh, whether I do it or don't do it, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: The clarity is there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then you need to protect it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, if it's, you know, in the direction of sensuality, in the direction of aversion, even if, at that moment, it won't be intense aversion that you
[SPEAKER_05]: Or intense sensuality that you gave up initially, you have to realize, well, but even a little bit is going to start taking me back to where I worked so hard to get away from, so why would I go back there?
[SPEAKER_05]: And that now becomes the way, another way for you to strengthen the mindfulness even more.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, just simply by abstaining from those actions, the perspective will grow even stronger, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: But also, if you see that, the mind's inclination, you could just as well ask, like, how will accepting this affect the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: As opposed to... Like, you could ask yourself, oh, will I get upset?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or will the mind get upset?
[SPEAKER_03]: If I refuse to accept this...
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, if you see it, even if you ask yourself, just like, oh, but even... how would the mind... where would the mind go if I accept this?
[SPEAKER_03]: You would see the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just kind of a different aspect of the same intention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the mind would present some option.
[SPEAKER_03]: And entertaining, let's say, like mentally, like thinking, how where accepting would lead, would reveal it just as much as thinking about where refusing that would lead.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aha, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just the different...
[SPEAKER_03]: But the thing is, without some perspective, when you would entertain accepting it, you would just be overwhelmed by the...
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the pleasure that's often then there is, like, basically falling into.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, you would see...
[SPEAKER_05]: The thing is, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: If you question yourself... Like, you might have already accepted it mentally.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why, more often than not, contemplating what happens if I just don't do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: What happens if...
[SPEAKER_05]: This thing...
[SPEAKER_05]: I never get to experience this thing ever again.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, that will reveal to you... because the direction of welcoming and accepting, it's kind of already bound with... and it's also already bound with a diminishing perspective.
[SPEAKER_05]: So then, to the extent that you already went in that direction, you won't be able to be clear about the fact that you are going in that direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: I get... it kind of muddles your own self-awareness, in other words.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why you can't engage in sensuality mindfully.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, having perspective over your sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's two incompatible things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality means not having perspective.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, more often than not, if you ask yourself, not even just bodily, physically, kind of giving in, what happens if I just don't think about this?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would already say, like, oh, wait.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there was a compulsion there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, eh... if you were going by your... again, your...
[SPEAKER_05]: If you had preconceived ideas of what's right and wrong, you might have thought, well, this is not a precept.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is even like, kind of, praiseworthy action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm helping other people or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would have emphasized that, rather than clearly, like, the mind is itching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this is the way that it's scratching itself right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yeah, like when you have inclinations of like overly denying things, like with kind of self-mortification, and you ask yourself like, oh, so what would happen if I stopped doing these?
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's another compulsion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that cannot possibly be the direction where actual peace lies.
[SPEAKER_05]: It might be less blinding than sensuality, just because relaxing is always easier than tightening, simply because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that the mind is... to the extent that there's concern, to the extent that there's need, to the extent that there's a dependence, it's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, oh, if I cannot survive without denying things that are not even
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed, aversion and delusion in themselves, that's that's a sign of the same hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: This also applies to when the mind starts to leap up at renunciation, as it says.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't at first, but eventually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because one progresses and sees that as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, it's about how... how close... oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Refining that renunciation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not just this kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: I was going to give things up for the sake of them.
[SPEAKER_04]: For the sake of... like, okay, well, I'm not going to... just... eat with a spoon anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just, eh... just give in to that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And...
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, if it's the actual renunciation on that level, you would see that it's... if you renounce the external things, it would be coming from the other direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: It would be coming from the direction of seeing how that will affect the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: You won't be giving things up just because you heard that there was this great monk who also gave these things up.
[SPEAKER_05]: You would see directly, for this mind, giving this up is going to lead to more awesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not usually what people do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They do it on... they have the inspiration to give things up, which is good, but then they judge what has to be given up by all sorts of external
[SPEAKER_01]: It sounds silly, but generally, it often is like, oh, I heard that there was such and such, and that's what he did, so let me do it too.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no direct discernment of like, okay, but is this actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Increasing my perspective is actually... Do I see that on account of doing this, the mind doesn't incline to sensual thoughts anymore?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or am I just like occupying myself with this other stuff and that's why the sensual thoughts arise... don't arise anymore?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just occupied with, I don't know, traveling around and living in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because I always have something to do and the next thing to take care of and worry about, that's why I don't have essential thoughts coming up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because, you know, you actually set up the renunciation properly and then the mind is generally turned away from that whole domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so in connection with this, can you be hindered by just one hindrance?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because sometimes people ask this question, like, what's your dominant hindrance?
[SPEAKER_02]: Having the impression, like, okay, so all the other four hindrances, I'm sort of, you know, there's just this one.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would that be an accurate discernment?
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe center stage.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is a kind of throne.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That particular entrance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That you can identify.
[SPEAKER_02]: But can that be, like... Is it possible for someone that... Can it be like, okay, there's just this entrance, center stage, and the other four, they're just not there now?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you would be relating to that hindrance in some way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it could be with the same hindrance or it could be with a different one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the thing is, of course, they are five.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in a way, you can recognize specific manifestations of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it works the same way as what we said before with the clarity of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not... you could say you have liability to clarity or liability to muddleness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, inclination towards clarity or inclination towards muddleness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And inclination towards clarity is the opposite of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, it doesn't matter what specifically that clarity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Directed towards, the point is, there is the broader sense of clarity there, and the same with the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter which one of them, specifically, or at least a determining factor is not going to be which one of them is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the fact that you're liable to have... Well, that you're effectively hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So then, whichever, like, for someone who gives in to sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: If bad things happen to them, they will be that much more prone to get angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: If, you know, there is some sort of threat to something that they value, there will be that much... of course, because that's what sensuality is, valuing and being attached to things, there will be that much more of a liability to be worried and concerned about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they don't have the stimulation that they're used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the whole laziness ends.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing until it comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would see the same works the other way around, like when somebody has been giving in to aversion, or even sadness, depression, and all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that they look for?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that they look for to uplift their mood and sensuality?
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is where the mood went down.
[SPEAKER_02]: To begin with, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you've been giving in to doubts and concerns and worries, the same thing happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the first promise of peace that you're going to see is, oh, let me just find some pleasant sense object to engage with, to calm the mind down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... that's... that's not the type of confidence that you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_02]: You keep yourself within the indices.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: You... you... well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of, eh... pushing away the specific manifestation by doing this action.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, so momentarily, it might, eh... cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the overall liability
[SPEAKER_01]: is being increased as a result of you giving it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, next thing comes up, you get bored of whatever pleasant object that was, and you will find out, wait, actually they didn't solve the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, boredom is also on the level of the hindrance or restlessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh yeah, boredom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what would happen if, I think I said that before, what would happen if you're thrown into solitary confinement after you've been indulging in sensuality and distractions for a whole day?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what will... how will that compare to when you haven't, when you have been restrained?
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, the boredom would hit you way, way harder, if you've... because it's exactly like abruptly cutting off the... like a train that's been moving in, I don't know, 200 miles per hour.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, but the boredom, whichever way you take it, whether it's restlessness or at least maybe boredom, the whole point is
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to be liable to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Precisely because of the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though you might see it as a completely separate thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You may not even see the connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was precisely what I was trying to get at.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the whole idea that you can just be like hindered by one hindrance and which is unrelated to the other four, that's quite a wrong understanding of the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_04]: I had a question, which is, I guess, in some ways related.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was about contentment.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, developing contentment would help to unhinder one.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's based off of this sutta where Sariputta is giving a discourse.
[SPEAKER_04]: At first, going forth is difficult, and then contentment is difficult to develop, and so on, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, I was wondering, maybe, what this contentment that Sariputta is referring to, so maybe it could be elaborated on.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, however, it's actually just what we've been discussing here, as well, about training the... training the mind, and...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, in some way, you're going to become careless when you're discontent with what's offered.
[SPEAKER_04]: At least, that's how I can see it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I'm not sure if that's completely what's being referred to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what would people think contentment is, in the right sense?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's... because, eh... some...
[SPEAKER_01]: Marginal amount of contentment, people might think, comes from the world, in centrality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what would be the difference between the contentment that comes from rightly chaining the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what would be the difference?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, I guess most obvious thing would be that the first would be dependent on... by definition, dependent on the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you'd recognize, oh, if this is taken away, or burns down, or dies, how would I be left with then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or how would that affect me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas the other one would basically
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll be completely independent of all of that, by definition.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's independent of external circumstances, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody who is inclined to a spirituality would recognize it as a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it has to ultimately be independent from internal circumstances as well, from deterioration of your own faculties.
[SPEAKER_01]: From arising of pressure on a mental level, because that's another circumstance, independent of unpleasant feelings, independent of unpleasant moods, independent of whatever mental things can come up, regardless of your wish for them not to come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when contentment depends on having a certain feeling for that matter,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the right type of contentment, because pleasant feeling is impermanent, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the right type of contentment is when it doesn't even matter when you feel this pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the only one that will survive everything, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the... eh... when... that's why it says that it's difficult to define contentment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's... it's...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's because the contentment that you have to find lies precisely in the direction that initially will be felt as discontent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, eh... giving up, acting out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even though you've already gone forth, as a sutta says, like you already went forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But despite going forth, you still haven't arrived at contentment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because sometimes you might think like, oh, if I just become a monk and just give up everything, I'll be happy with nothing, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's way more subtle than that, because you still will have the tendency to internally act out of pressure and seek to seek the contentment on the level of managing your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, like doing things that
[SPEAKER_01]: To get rid of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as that remains your your hope of achieving contentment, fundamentally, externally, you might be more restrained, but internally, you still maintain the same principle, which, ironically, is what makes you discontent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The need to have conditions be a certain way, even internally, that's what makes you discontent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because deep down, you know, it will deteriorate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And deep down, you know that you have to protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, compared to the actual contentment, it's not even... it's not even contentment, because it comes with the implicit worry and implicit kind of notice that it could be taken away at any time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, arriving at the right contentment will require, to some extent,
[SPEAKER_01]: Enduring discontent, but that discontent, you have to see that it's not because of the restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not because you're not giving in to the pressure that you're discontented.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're discontented simply because you're resisting the pain of not giving in to the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you stop resisting the pain of not giving in to the pressure, that's exactly what the contentment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not resisting... because we ask ourselves, why am I resisting?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize there's no justification for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you give that up, which, of course, sounds easier than it actually is, you realize, oh, yeah, I was discontent because I myself was making myself so, through my own wrong way of attending things, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still implying, to some extent, that I need to find a solution to this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas,
[SPEAKER_01]: The attitude of needing to find a solution is the reason why the pain is a problem in the first place.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, virtue would be purified?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there would be no way of you acting out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, only then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, before that, you would be... Would it be like a pleasantness of a more virtuous life?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, still, to some extent, you would still be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Valuing, certainly, the things of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you would be giving them up because you hope that you will get something in return later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see directly here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, the... like, sensuality takes time, but the dhamma is presently evident.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't see, in that presently evident sense, why giving these things up is already better.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be thinking like, oh, later on something will happen that will kind of make all of this worthwhile, or something like that, and that's another sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within the pain you have to finally escape, and that's when it will be independent of anything, any circumstance, any deterioration of conditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think then there's what it says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you do find contentment, then it wouldn't take long.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's one extra.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's hard then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Practicing in line with the teaching.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But for someone who practices in line with the teaching, would it take long?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that connects with what we've been saying before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might actually be contented, factually.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind has developed the clarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sees things that go against the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sees them as unpleasant, as not worth it, as a charcoal pit, as the suttas would say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet still, practicing the line of the dhamma isn't automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a guarantee, it doesn't follow, that just because you're contented, you would automatically practice the line of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which sounds kind of counterintuitive, but factually, that's how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that sutta where it says, a monk might enter the first jhāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: And somebody might think, oh, he will never go back to sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha gives a simile, it's like when, you know, like when the... when it's been really dry, and then dust starts accumulating, and then it rains, and then somebody thinks, oh, this dust will never come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and it goes all the way to the 4th jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... it's... it's... That is the factual, most accurate contentment that you could arrive at.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and yet it says, but even then, after achieving that, somebody might even disrobe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the monk, and that's what the... that's exactly what he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, of course, that doesn't mean that, eh... that doesn't mean that the contentment
[SPEAKER_01]: That we're referring to, like, factually, it has to be outside of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the time, what people would call jhāna, isn't actually outside of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's even a deeper problem there.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, even if you reach the real deal, yeah, the mind is still, in a way, precisely because of you having reached that greater perspective, you might disregard
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else that you had to do in order to arrive at it, because it feels like, oh, well, the mind is, as Atsuta says, the elephant that's now invincible in battle, that can take everything, like swords, spears, and everything without reacting, and so you send it into battle, but it wasn't actually ready, and then it dies.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there comes a point when you can't lose mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, that point would come already, like... yeah, the point when you can't lose mindfulness is when you have samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's... that factually is like, even if you want to, you can't lose it.
[SPEAKER_05]: The problem is, if you, factually, without losing it, do certain things, you will suddenly find that you lost it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you were not losing it while you were doing those things, or at least it didn't feel like you were.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when you turn around, you realize, actually, it wasn't there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it works, because it's that indirect dimension.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that indirect kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the kind of ultimate background of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would start taking it for granted, basically, that you would start doing things thinking like, oh, well, yeah, the hindrances are gone, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that gradual kind of inclining, as the Buddha would say, what you incline, what you frequently think and ponder about, that's what the mind inclines to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a gradual kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: Bit by bit, pushing it back in that direction, and then you will find, oh, actually it is... now it's more on that side than the right side that I had it in initially.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one thing that people would really struggle to understand when we say, like, the... in order to enter the first jhāna, you factually have to give up even the liability to the five hindrances, not just, like, specific manifestations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then it would sound like, also, you're saying you have to basically become an arahant in order to enter the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the liability to the hindrances is factually gone at that time, whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean that they will not come back.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if you incline the mind, if you give in to the things that, at that time, don't feel like they're a problem, the hindrances will return.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not immediately, but they will return.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there's no removing the liability, to the liability, of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just that they are... staying there.
[SPEAKER_05]: By staying there, by staying in the state where you're not liable to hindrances, then, then, yeah, you would... any inclination to
[SPEAKER_01]: Turn the mind back towards the hindrances, it would be gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you wouldn't fall away from it out of the unwholesome reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would fall away from it just because of circumstantial reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not like someone who's not free from sensuality, who falls away because factually they start, like, the the fetters and stuff, get them to incline the mind in the opposite direction again.